Abdul Rehman

Intelligent Systems Engineering, Indiana University Bloomington 700 N Woodlawn Ave Bloomington, IN - 47408

■ 8127784435 | ■ abrehman@iu.edu | 🏫 abrehman94.github.io | 🖸 github.com/abrehman94

Summary.

Ph.D. student with 8+ years of systems software development (6 years of full time industrial position) and systems research (2 years) experience. During my time in industry I have worked on UEFI firmware, Nucleus RTOS and NVMe virtualization. For past two years, my focus has been on serverless computing, linux scheduling and machine learning. I have added Rust, eBPF and deep learning approach using pyTorch to my toolbox. I am working under the guidance of Prateek Sharma at Indiana University Bloomington. I enjoy diving deep into complex problems, trying to find the last ounce of performance boost in myraid of interconnected components.

Education

Indiana University Bloomington

Bloomington, United States

PhD in Intelligent Systems Engineering

Aug 2022 - Present

Advisor: Prateek Sharma

- Research area: cloud computing
- CGPA 3.91/4.00
- Courses: Applied Algorithms, Cloud Computing, Compilers, Operating Systems, Deep Learning, Signal Processing using Machine Learning

Research Assistant Aug 2022 - Present

- Current Research: Targeted Scheduling for a serverless platform (Linux, eBPF, SchedExt, Rust)
- Development of Realtime Data Analytics System using MQTT, InfluxDB and Torch Serve (see projects).
- · Contriubted to the development of a serveless platform written in Rust ground up (publication).

National University of Sciences and Technology

Islamabad, Pakistan

Aug 2011 - June 2015

Electrical Engineering

- CGPA 3.92/4.00
- Courses: Embedded Systems, Digital System Design, Digital Signal Processing

Publications

Published

[1] Alexander Fuerst, **Abdul Rehman**, Prateek Sharma. Ilúvatar: A Fast Control Plane for Serverless Computing. *High-Performance Parallel and Distributed Computing (HPDC)* '23, Acceptance Rate 21%

Under Preparation

[1] **Abdul Rehman**, Prateek Sharma. λ Sched: A fine grained scheduling solution for an Energy Efficient Serverless Platform. *pending*, submission

Projects

Targeted CPU Scheduling for a serverless platform

Indiana University Bloomington

Mar 2024 - Present

- A custom CPU scheduling solution (using SchedExt framework) that uses function metadata to improve the performance of the serverless
 platform.
- Project Page: https://abrehman94.github.io/projects/schedext_based_scheduling.html

Edge-IoT-Analytics-Box - Extensible Data Analytics System

Indiana University Bloomington

Dec 2023 - May 2024

- A data analytics system that can be deployed on edge devices (protyped on Jetson Orin) to perform real-time data analytics.
- Project Page: https://abrehman94.github.io/projects/dataanalytics.html

Iluvatar a Serverless Control Plane in Rust

Indiana University Bloomington

Aug 2022 - May 2023

- A radical approach to serverless computing monolithic, worker centric platform.
- Project Page: https://abrehman94.github.io/projects/iluvatar.html

November 14, 2024

Work Experience

Siemens Industry Software Inc.

Mobile, AL, United States

Senior Software Engineer - Hypervisor Team

Mar 2021 - Sep 2021

- Siemens Hypervisor support on Intel Embedded Processors Elkhartlake (2021).
 - Release critical bug-fixes: ACPI parser, AHCI Virtualization, NVMe Virtualization
 - Mentoring a new engineer.

Mentor Graphics a Siemens Business

Lahore, Pakistan Jan 2020 - Mar 2021

Senior Software Engineer - Hypervisor Team

- · Virtualized UEFI interface
 - Design and development of a non-volatile variable caching infrastructure to avoid SMI generation and provide real time gurantees for Guest RTOS.
- NVMe Virtualization
 - Performance improvement of NVMe virtualization infrastructure from 700 MB/s to 1.5 GB/s. Improved the infrastructure to process requests across SMP cores.
 - Led a team of two engineers to deliver the project.

Software Engineer - Hypervisor Team

Aug 2016 - Jan 2020

- Virtualized UEFI interface
 - Implementation of UEFI boot support for Guest OS (Windows, Linux, RTOS) on Siemens Type 1 Hypervisor.
- Design and development of a UEFI driver for Intel Graphics Device (IGD) to allow early graphics for Linux and Windows guests.
- NVMe Virtualization
 - Design and development of the infrastructure. Specifically, interrupt handling (PCI MSI-X capability) and I/O queue segregation for the virtual devices and hardware backend.
 - Adapting the Linux NVMe driver to act as a Paravirtualized Client for testing purpose.
- Feature Releases for Mentor Embedded Hypervisor (Type 1)
 - Design and development of VT-d DMAR/IOMMU driver to allow device isolation and memory remapping of guests.

Software Engineer - Embedded UI Graphics Team

Jun 2015 - Aug 2016

- · Qt GUI Framework version 5.4 on Nucleus RTOS
 - Porting of the framework based on a previous work for Qt 4.0.
 - Performance optimization of the ported framework.

Awards

2023 **Travel Grant,** High-Performance Parallel and Distributed Computing 2023

Orlando, USA

Appreciation Certificates: exceptional debugging skills, high quality work, Mentor a Siemens Business Lahore, Pakistan

Skills

2016

Programming Languages Rust, C/C++, Bash, Python (Pandas, NumPy)

Application Level Distributed Systems (serverless, InfluxDB), Containerization(Docker, containerd)

Close to hardware eBPF, Linux Kernel, Type 1 Hypervisors (ACRN/XEN/MEHV/Siemens), UEFI Driver, ACPI, x86, Lauterbach Trace-32 Debuggers

Machine Learning PyTorch, Application of Deep Learning approach

Tools tmux, vim, ssh, perfetto

November 14, 2024 2